Guide to the Henry Walter Papers 1950-2017 MS 3016
New-York Historical Society
- Series I. Public Relations Files. Abraham D. Beame, 1961-2000s (bulk, 1969-1977); 22.92 Linear feet
  - Subseries I.B. Mayoralty Years, 1960s-2000s (bulk, 1974-1977); 14.17 Linear feet
    - Working Files. 1977 October (2 folders) (Offsite-box 24, Folder 16-17)
      Includes the Report in Support of Indirect Source Permit for Westway: Response to Hearing Officer Recommendation of September 13, 1977 prepared by the Westway Expediting Council (Oct 7); theprogram for the Citicorp Center Dedication Ceremonies, in the shape of the building (Oct 12); and a brochure issued in connection with the Algonquin Hotel's 75th anniversary ((Oct 18).
    - Press Releases. 1977 November-December (Offsite-box 25, Folder 1)
      Includes the Response of the City of New York to the Report of the Staff of the Securities and Exchange Commission on Transactions in Securities of the City of New York.
    - Working Files. 1977 November-December (Offsite-box 25, Folder 2)
    - Working Files. Undated, 1976-1977? (Offsite-box 25, Folder 3)
      Includes a few documents that could not be specifically placed as to date, but are likely from 1976-77.
    - Post-Beame Mayoralty, 1978-2000s (Offsite-box 25, Folder 4)
      Includes various documents related to Beame including a speech identified only by date (12 March 1979) in which Beame reflects on his administration in the context of disagreeing with those who see the steady decline of cities; arrangements for a reunion of Beame staff members (1983); newspaper articles; and an undated artifact: a plastic bag from the Daily News bearing the saying "We're Glad to be Back."
- Series II. Public Relations Files. Harrison J. Goldin, 1976-1990s (bulk, 1978-1989); 12 Linear feet
  The series includes Henry Walter's working files while in the employ of Comptroller Harrison Jay Goldin. The files primarily hold Goldin's speeches and drafts of speeches (often multiple copies and versions), drafts of articles for the Comptroller's Report monthly newsletter, final published copies of that newsletter, newspaper clippings and photocopies of clippings, letters from organizations requesting Goldin's appearance at events, miscellaneous publicity-related correspondence, staff notes and memos, Walter's weekly timesheets and other administrative matters (e.g. vacation requests). There are some press releases and schedules; the schedule primarly relate to Goldin's appearances at which speeches/remarks are needed, not Goldin's overall appointment schedule. In addition to speeches related to Goldin's position as Comptroller, the files include materials related to Goldin's campaigns for re-election, as State Comptroller (1978), and as Mayor (1989).
  When received by N-YHS, some of the material in this series was roughly foldered, while most was unfoldered in uneven, rough chronological chunks. In September 2021, most of the material was arranged by archivist Larry Weimer in rough chronological order by month/year (not by day). Some material was left as is in the original donated folders, when that seemed to be meaningful or useful in some way. At the time (September 2021), the series was still restricted as per the gift agreement (restricted during the life of Goldin), so the material was just roughly processed to have a good working box inventory before the collection was sent off-site for storage. In its current form, the series is accessible, though it could stand some refinement.
  - Comptroller's Report (Newsletters), 1976-1977 (Offsite-box 32)
  - Working Files (2), 1977-1978 January (Offsite-box 32)
  - Working Notes, 1977-1979 (Offsite-box 32)
  - Files for 1978 (14 folders) (Offsite-box 32)
  - Files for 1978 (32 folders) (Offsite-box 33)
    One of the folders holds a set of speeches concluding with one from 1979.
  - Files for 1979 (10 folders) (Offsite-box 33)
  - Files for 1979 (2 folders) (Offsite-box 34)
  - Files for 1980 (9 folders) (Offsite-box 34)
  - Files for 1981 (1 folder) (Offsite-box 34)
  - Files for 1981 (11 folders) (Offsite-box 35)
  - Files for 1982 (3 folders) (Offsite-box 35)
  - Files for 1982 (2 folders) (Offsite-box 36)
  - Files for 1983 (8 folders) (Offsite-box 36)
  - Files for 1983 (1 folder) (Offsite-box 37)
  - Files for 1984 (9 folders) (Offsite-box 37)
  - Files for 1985 (7 folders) (Offsite-box 38)
  - Files for 1986 (5 folders) (Offsite-box 38)
  - Files for 1986 (5 folders) (Offsite-box 39)
  - Files for 1987 (6 folders) (Offsite-box 39)
  - Files for 1987 (1 folder) (Offsite-box 40)
  - Files for 1988 (7 folders) (Offsite-box 40)
  - Files for 1989 (4 folders) (Offsite-box 40)
  - Files for 1989 (15 folders) (Offsite-box 41)
  - Files for 1989 (10 folders) (Offsite-box 42)
  - Timesheets (1 folder), 1980s (Offsite-box 42)
    Most of Walter's weekly timesheets are in the regular working files. Some from various years in the 1980s, however, were filed separately in this folder, along with some other administrative documents and contact/phone lists.
  - Comptroller Report topics (1 folder), 1988 (Offsite-box 42)
    Holds a subject index for at least some of the 1988 issues. Also has random copies of some of the report articles from the 1980s.
  - Clippings. Joey Adams's column, with subject index (5 folders), 1979-1986 (Offsite-box 42)
    Includes clips of Adams's "Strictly for Laughs" newspaper column, organized alphabetically by subject, with an index.
  - History of the Comptroller's Office (1 folder), 1970s-1980s (Offsite-box 42)
    Includes various documents concerning descriptions of the history, purpose, organization, etc. of the Comptroller.
  - Post-Comptrollership (1 folder), 1990s (Offsite-box 42)
    Holds a few documents related to Goldin after he left office, primarily dating from 1990.
  - Comptroller's Monthly Newsletter (5 bound volumes), 1976-1984 (Offsite-box 43)
    These bound volumes include issues that pre-date Walter's employment by Goldin and so are not in the working files. The bound copies end in 1984; later years are found in Walter's working files.
  - Booklet. Presentation to Moody's Investors Service re: New York City's General Obligation Revenue Anticipation Notes, 1979 Series C and 1979 Series D (Offsite-box 43)
  - 2 reports issued by the Office of Policy Management, 1989 December (Offsite-box 43)
    Holds: "Cork in the bottle: New York City's nursing home shortage" and "Now we are four: Boarder babies growing up in foster care: A follow-up study."
- Series III. Public Relations Files. Other, 1951-1993 (bulk, 1960s); 1.17 Linear feet
  The series is arranged by topic, in roughly chronological order.
  The series includes documents, much of which was prepared by Henry Walter, of a public relations nature for various public figures, other than Abraham Beame and Harrison Goldin. Most notably, these include Walter's files as Press Secretary for Robert M. Morgenthau during Morgenthau's campaign for Governor of New York in 1962. These files include press releases, speeches and remarks, drafts, correspondence, schedules, and campaign travel arrangements. The series also includes press releases issued by Walter in his capacity as the Director of Public Information for the newly-formed New York City Department of Highways (1963-64). Also from the 1960s is a folder of campaign brochures and other ephemera related to former reporter and Democratic candidate Martin J. Steadman's campaign for Congress from the 4th Congressional District (1966), with a letter from Steadman to Walter thanking him for his help and support during the campaign.
  The series also includes a small amount of speechwriting done by Walter in the 1990s. These include drafts of remarks concerning retirement financial security by Cuyler Findlay of the AARP Investment Program at Scudder Investor Services (1991) and work Walter did for former Westchester County Executive Alfred DelBello, including drafts of a speech and an article on the international transboundary movement of hazardous waste (1990), business and jobs (1992), and for a public affairs program on Cablevision focused on crime and punishment (1993).
  The series includes a small amount of miscellaneous documents concerning Walter himself, including his 1960 remarks to the Air Pollution Control Association on the topic "The Role of Public Media"; a guest pass to the 1964 New York State Democratic Convention; his 1970 resume; a letter leading to his hiring on to Comptroller Beame's staff; two family photographs; "I Care" and "Stevenson" lapel pins; two articles written for the world-Telegram and Sun; and other documents.
  - Robert Morgenthau Campaign Files (12 folders), 1962 (Offsite-box 29, Folder 1-12)
  - New York City Department of Highways Press Releases (5 folders), 1963-1964 (Offsite-box 25, Folder 5-9)
    Includes the first Annual Report of the Highways Department (issued January 2, 1964, for the year 1963).
  - Martin J. Steadman Campaign, 1966 (Offsite-box 28, Folder 10)
  - Cuyler Findlay Speech, 1991 (Offsite-box 28, Folder 11)
  - Alfred B. DelBello. Waste Management (Projects 39 & 40), Circa 1976, 1990 (Offsite-box 25, Folder 10)
    Includes circa 1976 campaign literature for DelBello's re-election as Westchester County Executive.
  - Alfred B. DelBello. Business & Jobs, 1992 (Offsite-box 25, Folder 11)
  - Alfred B. DelBello. Crime & Punishment (2 folders), 1993 (Offsite-box 25, Folder 12-13)
  - Henry Walter. Miscellaneous, 1951-1970s (Offsite-box 28, Folder 12)
- Series IV. Inner Circle Show, 1956-2017; 0.83 Linear feet
  The series is arranged in chronological order.
  Formed in 1922, the Inner Circle of New York Political Journalists (known commonly as the Inner Circle) is an organization of New York City political reporters and journalists that performs an annual amateur parody show lampooning city, state and national political figures. The show is a fundraiser for charity and has become a major event in which political figures, including the mayor of New York, now commonly perform. Henry Walter became a member in 1956, served as the organization's president in 1963, and performed in at least some of the shows. He also collected materials from the annual shows and those documents form this series.
  The series includes the programs from the annual Inner Circle shows for every year from 1956 to 1999. For the 2000s, programs are missing from 2000, 2009, 2010, 2012, and 2013; the final year in the series collected by Walter is 2014. The programs include satirical cover art illustrating the theme of the year's show (which is often linked to a current pop cultural reference), the cast of characters and the performers, the lyrics to the show's many musical numbers, and reference to the commonly-recognized tune to which the lyrics were sung. For most years, the seating chart for the event is also included. The series also holds other documents for many of the years, including dress rehearsal programs (the dress rehearsal was held before the main event for members, family and friends), invitations/flyers (bearing the program's cover art), tickets to the dress rehearsal or President's reception, some scripts, and some miscellaneous documents, such as invitations to members to attend Inner Circle meetings.
  The series also includes the program and seating chart for the 2017 show, the first to follow Walter's death in November 2016. The program includes a memorial statement for Walter on page 28 and a photo of him visiting the rehearsal on page 23 (4th row from top, 2nd from left).
  - Inner Circle Documents (7 folders), 1956-1984 (Offsite-box 30, Folder 1-7)
  - Inner Circle Documents (9 folders), 1985-2017 (Offsite-box 31, Folder 1-9)
- Series V. Print Matter, 1950-2001; 3.75 Linear feet in three boxes and 1 oversize folder
  The series is arranged with the New York City directories first, followed by other print matter. The other print matter is arranged in the numerical sequence (1-255) of the items as found in the inventory provided by a member of Henry Walter's family. This sequence is generally chronological, except that some oversize items from the 1980s are found at the end of the list. Copies of the detailed inventory are found in the two boxes that hold the other print matter.
  The series includes a diverse and idiosyncratic mix of printed materials dating from the 1950s to 2001, though mostly from the 1970s and 1980s. Very generally, the material concerns economic, political, cultural, and public policy matters. Most of the materials were created by New York City-based organizations, concern New York City matters, and seem targeted to a New York City audience, but some are of state-wide or national scope. The bulk of the series includes some form of periodical, especially newsletters, newspapers, magazines, and series of technical or policy reports. But with few exceptions there are no extended runs of any of the individual titles; most titles are represented by only a few issues, often only the first number of the title. Aside from periodicals, the series holds a variety of single issue documents of interest, such as commemorative booklets, souvenir programs, annual reports, calendars of events, publicity materials, and the like.
  Newsletters perhaps form most of the series. These newsletters were created by government agencies, or groups within those agencies, for internal distribution or for the general public; public policy interest groups; political figures; commercial institutions; trade associations; and other organizations. There are also many small newspapers created for distribution within a specific New York City neighborhood, organization, or constituency.
  A detailed list of the printed material was provided by the donor's family and is housed with the documents. The container list below summarizes most of these items at the folder level.
  In addition to these miscellaneous printed material the series also includes several New York City official directories, known as the "Green Book," from the 1950s to the 1980s used by Henry Walter.
  - New York City Official Directories ("Green Book"), 1950-1989 (Offsite-box 27, Item 1-25)
    Includes Walter's copies for the years 1950, 1953, 1954, 1956, 1957, 1958, 1962, 1963, 1965, 1966, 1967, 1968, 1970, 1976, and 1980 through 1988-89.
  - Print Matter (#1-13), 1950s (Offsite-box 25, Folder 14)
    * Brochure for the NBC Symphony Summer Concerts for 1951, with four programs (10 June-15 July)
    * Program from Town Hall recital hall for the 2 May 1952 performance of Cham-ber Huang
    * WQXR's Monthly Guide to Dining Out (August 1952)
    * Booklet commemorating the 31st anniversary of The Jumble-Shop restaurant in Greenwich Village (1952)
    * Report on New York City Slum Clearance Projects Under Title I by Private Capital with Federal and City Aid by the Committee on Slum Clearance (April 1956)
    * Bay Ridge Home Reporter (14-21 June 1956)
    * Booklet The Insurance on Your Apartment by the LeFrak Organization (circa 1957)
    * Joint Study of Arterial Facilities in the New York-New Jersey Metropolitan Area (November 1957)
    * Taxi Weekly (20 November 1957)
    * Guild Telegram (Vol 1, No. 1), announcing the slate of elected guild officials, including Henry Walter as Chairman
    * Periodicals, reprints, and other documents.
  - Print Matter (#14-24), 1960s (Offsite-box 25, Folder 15)
    * New York Central Railroad, Hudson Division timetable (29 April 1962)
    * New York State Democratic Convention program (1962)
    * Program and seating chart for the Legislative Correspondents' Association banquet and parody show "Vial Ventures, or Find the Fount 'N Blow!" (1963)
    * Commemorative book for the opening of the Verrazano-Narrows Bridge, Spanning the Narrows (1964)
    * Two Better Business Bureau pamphlets
    * Issues 1 and 2 of the weekly Mayday, edited by Andrew Kopkind, James Ridgeway, and Robert Sherrill (October 1968)
    * Conservative Journal, issued by New York State Young Americans for Freedom (September 1968)
    * other periodicals and reprints.
  - Print Matter (#25-40), 1960s (Offsite-box 25, Folder 16)
    * Four public affairs pamphlets from the Public Affairs Committee
    * "Freedom and the Public Schools" lecture by David I. Ashe (1969)
    * Several issues and six posters of the Marshall McLuhan DEW-LINE, issued by the Human Development Corporation (1969)
    * Annual report for 1969 of the New York City Police Department
    * Marketing brochure for the Americana Hotel.
  - Print Matter (#41-54), circa 1970-1972 (Offsite-box 25, Folder 17)
    * Flyer for the non-profit Community Environments
    * Two pamphlets about gold from the Federal Reserve
    * The Lotos Club centennial booklet (1970)
    * Two issues of the Marshall McLuhan DEW-LINE (1970)
    * First number of newsletter for buyers/sellers, Everything for Everybody (1970)
    * First number of newsletter from the New York City Human Resources Administration, People (1970)
    * First number of newsletter EAC (Environmental Action Coalition) News (1970)
    * A Tour of New York City & the Statue of Liberty picture book
    * Booklet (souvenir?) for the musical Grease
    * Mostly Mozart program (1972)
    * First number of newspaper Media & Consumer (1972).
  - Print Matter (#55-67), 1973 (Offsite-box 26, Folder 1)
    * New York Convention & Visitors Bureau brochures (1973)
    * Three numbers of a newspaper sent to New York area college students, The Press (1973)
    * Three issues, including first two numbers, of newsletter, The Commuter, published for the Harlem-Hudson-New Haven Lines by the Penn Central Transportation Company (1973)
    * Issue of the Armed Forces Comptroller (1973)
    * Con Edison's Customer Handbook and related brochures (1973)
    * New York Press Club's 25th anniversary edition of Byline magazine (1973)
    * Promotional packet for the publication National Star (1973).
  - Print Matter (#68-85), 1974-1975 (Offsite-box 26, Folder 2)
    * Handbook New York, Your Host prepared by the City Commission for the United Nations and for the Consular Corps (1974)
    * Five issues of Notes from the Municipal Reference and Research Center (1974)
    * Three issues of newsletter, The Commuter, (1974)
    * Datebook Life in America from the Metropolitan Museum of Art (1975)
    * National Urban League booklet The Struggle for Equality of Educational Opportunity (1975)
    * Empire State Report (1975)
    * First number of the Upper East Side's newsletter East Apple (1975)
    * Other periodicals.
  - Print Matter (#86-96), 1976 (Offsite-box 26, Folder 3)
    * New York Life Insurance Company's annual report for 1976
    * (Souvenir?) program for the play, The Belle of Amherst with Julie Harris
    * Operation Sail 1976 booklet
    * Tall Ships '76 souvenir program
    * Checklist booklet for the exhibition The Tulip & the Rose: Seeds of Queens History at the Queens Museum
    * Booklet The U.S. Customs House on Bowling Green by Brendan Gill
    * Five booklets in the Black Perspectives on the Bicentennial series published by the National Urban League.
  - Print Matter (#97-102), 1976 (Offsite-box 26, Folder 4)
    * Calendar of events for Bicentennial observances July 4th in Old New York
    * Two booklets concerning the International Naval Review
    * Issue of New York Press Club's Byline magazine
    * Municipal Assistance Corporation's (MAC) annual report for 1976
    * Publicity packet for the Museum of Holography exhibition Through the Looking Glass.
  - Print Matter (#103-115), 1977 (Offsite-box 26, Folder 5)
    * The Story of Money comic book and other Federal Reserve Bank publications
    * An Italian wine guide distributed by Chatham Square Liquor Co.
    * First number of The Bulletin Board, the newsletter of New York's block associations
    * First two numbers of For Your Information, the newsletter of the Health Systems Agency of New York City
    * First number of Focus, newsletter of the New York Regional Office of the Anti-Defamation League of B'nai B'rith
    * Con Edison's special issue of its periodical Around the System for September 1977, reporting on the July black-out
    * First number of newspaper Politicks & Other Human Interests
    * First number of Museum of Holography's newsletter, The Whole Message
    * First number of newspaper, The News World: Manhattan.
  - Print Matter (#116-135), 1978 (Offsite-box 26, Folder 6)
    * Two issues, including the first number, of the newspaper, The Trib
    * Second number of Focus, newsletter of the New York Regional Office of the Anti-Defamation League of B'nai B'rith
    * First three numbers of Borough President Howard Golden's Brooklyn Newsletter
    * First four numbers of the Federal Regional Council newsletter, Region II In View
    * First three numbers of Mayor Edward I. Koch's Mayor's Newsletter
    * An issue of the Federation of Citywide Block Associations's newsletter, News
    * First two numbers of the newspaper City News
    * First two numbers of the Metropolitan New York Nursing Home Association's newsletter, Health Care News
    * An issue of newspaper Politicks & Other Human Interests
    * Calendar of events for the "World of Our Fathers" Jewish Heritage Festival.
  - Print Matter (#136-156), 1979 (Offsite-box 26, Folder 7)
    * First numbers of various newsletters: New York County Lawyers' Association's Legislative Update, Neighborhood Women Network News, Bronx borough president Stanley Simon's senior citizen newsletter, Association of Concessionaires of New York City's Concessionaire News, Citizens Housing & Planning Council's Reporter, National Council on Compulsive Gambling's Newsletter, Department of General Services's DGS Reporter, Pace University Graduate School of Business's GSB Outlook, and Columbia's Career Development Bulletin; World Traders' Atlas, issued by the Port Authority of New York & New Jersey
    * An issue of The Hunger Project's Quantum Leap
    * First two numbers of The American Lawyer
    * Two numbers of borough president Golden's Brooklyn Newsletter
    * First three numbers of Group Health, Inc's GHI News
    * Summary of survey responses compiled by the League of Women Voters of the Tri-State Metropolitan Region.
  - Print Matter (#157-175), circa 1980-1981 (Offsite-box 26, Folder 8)
    * First number of various newsletters: Department of General Services's Operation Greenthumb Newsletter and Wires Telecommunity News, Greater New York Conference on Soviet Jewry's Currents, New York Employment Council's newsletter, Community Council of Greater New York's Impact, Citizens Budget Commission's CBC Quarterly
    * First two numbers of newsletter The Queens Letter
    * Metro-North Railroad brochure A Guide to Passenger Safety
    * Two issues of The Library for the Blind and Physically Handicapped's Library Notebook
    * An issue of Elmcor Youth and Adult Activities, Inc.'s newsletter Elmcor Express
    * Other brochures.
  - Print Matter (#176-199), 1982-1984 (Offsite-box 26, Folder 9)
    * First numbers of various newsletters: Theatre Times, Public Papers of the Fund for the City of New York, the Department of Probation's Communicator, Assembly Speaker Stanley Fink's Special Report, The Bowery's Bank Notes, the Economic Capital Corporation of New York's Newsline, the Department of Records and Information Services's Notes, Metro-North's Mileposts, and the New York Republican State Committee's Greenburgh Gazette
    * First number of the political newspaper, Talking Turkey
    * Two issues of Women in Touch, a newsletter from the Committee for Women's Concerns of the Comptroller's Office
    * Three issues, including the first, of bulletins from Ellen's Coffee Cafe on Broadway
    * First two numbers of the Brooklyn Paper's Downtown News
    * Municipal Assistance Corporation's (MAC) annual report for 1982
    * Brooklyn Bridge centennial brochure